Earlier we've seen how we could create a motion graph starting from one big animation
and today as an introduction to reinforcement learning we will see how we could use that motion
graph to build a runtime animation controller. Hi, I'm Jérôme and today's paper will be
pre-computing avatar behavior from human motion data, a paper from 2004. So the idea of that paper
is to start from a motion graph. So what I've done is that I've saved a bunch of information from
the notebook with the motion graph. So I don't have to recompute the motion graph from scratch.
I would already have all the transitions and all that kind of stuff saved for me. So what I've done
is of course loading all the libraries and then I will load my character and I've also added all
the foot contact so I can do a quick IK pass to stabilize my foot at run time. I have a sphere
for debug and here's the informations I have from the motion graph data. So I have the animation
that I've used to do that locomotion. I have the window size that was used. I have the frame
validity. So I know inside of that big animations which frames are meant to be used and which are
invalid. I had a bunch of range that I didn't want to use. And I get the local minima. So basically
all the time, all the places where I could have transitions. So that's all informations coming
from the motion graph. What I would do is quickly compute the foot contact again. So I know when
when I have a contact on the ground.
And as a reminder, here is the animation
that was used to build a motion graph.
So this is the entire animation here.
So a bunch of locomotions walking along
and then see that's the range
that I want to use the teleportations.
And then I get higher turns, smaller turns
and all that kind of stuff.
So that's what was used when we were doing the motion graph.
Now, I will recreate the motion graph here.
I only have all the transitions possible.
But what I would do is that I will do it the same way
as the paper has done it in this case.
So instead of using the motion graph with every node,
being a bunch of frames and every edge,
being the jump where you could go.
What we will do is that we will turn this graph
into a state and action graph,
which is tens of terms that you will hear a lot
when we start to talk about reinforcement learning
and all of those.
So now it's a bunch of states.
So instead of having all my frames of animation and jump,
I only have the state and the state represents one frame
where I can take a decision.
So it doesn't represent an animation anymore
and represent a pose.
And the action itself is the animation you could take,
you could do to reach the next state.
So each state is one pose and each actions
are actually the animations that leads the next state.
So I will build the graph in this way.
So I will have a state,
and each state will have a bunch of actions,
and the actions will be knowing the starting frame
of animations and the end frame of animations.
So that really the action that has the animations.
And the way you compute this kind of stuff,
basically you start by creating an action of one frame
creating an action of one frame between every states as in this case all the
bees so you create all the actions then you add what I've done is I'm adding all
the transitions that were coming from the computed motion graph that says you
could jump from here to here and that kind of stuff so that's all the action
that represents the jumps.
And then you will basically pick one of any states.
And then you check its first action,
and then you check the state.
And if that state has only one action,
you basically collapse the edge.
So you make the edge longer and longer and longer.
And then basically all the states
that don't have any edges anymore discarded.
So that's how I've done it here.
I get all my edges and then I start to collapse them
if they don't have anything that need to lead to.
And when you've done all of that,
basically you end up with 540 different states.
So that's the number of states I have.
And each of those states have at least two actions
they can pick from. What I would do then, because I have all those states and the states
that themselves are the actual animations, I will start to pre-compute a bunch of stuff
on those states just to make my life easier when I will keep going through the paper and
I need to play back a bunch of stuff. So what I would do is that now every actions I know
exactly where they start from and up to where they go. So I will store the trajectory of the root
motion directly in the state. Remember my animations is all over the place in world space
and I only want to be able to move everything into local space. So everything I will do
is that every start of the actions I take the first position as being neutral and bring it back
back to zero zero. And I take the trajectory as a local trajectory based on the first frame.
And thanks to that one, I can have a local trajectory that basically is just the amount
of displacement I have along every frame. So when I would want to play back the animation,
the only thing I have to care about now is always adding the amount of trajectory, local
trajectory at every frame. I don't need anymore to compute all the transform, bringing back
the character, realigning them, all that kind of stuff, because basically all my motion is local
to the previous frame that was played anyway. So that's what I'm doing here. I go through every
states, I go through every actions and then I pre-compute the local trajectory. So all of that
now it's local to the frame of the state itself and then I compute the local trajectory that's
just the offsets between frame to frame and I store that inside of the action so now my action has
the trajectory it's expect and what I will do so far every time I was doing a paper
I was pre-computing an animation and playing back that animation now what I want to be
to be able to do is to be runtime. So I will actually create an animation player which just
means that I stored informations of which frame I'm playing and what is the positions I'm in space
and then I will have the foot lock mechanism. Basically that one is just really a simple
like it and just check if the foot or it's even only checking if the toe is on the ground
and if it is, I don't allow it to move from frame to frame and then if it's not, I just release
that IK with a blend just to get a soft release every time I connect. And then the animation
player itself basically knows which action is playing. It knows the frame of inside of that
actions, where am I inside of along this action. I get the position and coordinates of really the
pose of the character that it computes. I know which frame was played last. If I'm doing a transition,
so am I blending between two animations and that kind of stuff.
And so what happens is that you ticket every frame saying I need you to compute the next frame
and if it has an action it goes and play the next frame of that action
and when you reach the end of the action it just put the actions to none and says
I have nothing left to play and what happened is that you could set an action and basically
you add the new action to the next stuff and so on and so on so that's what the player would do.
and if we go and see what happens now I get the animation player so I will
start from my player and the only thing I will do is I start with tell him you
play you you tick the player the only thing that if you don't have any action
to do you will play you basically check in which state you should be you pick
any randomly any action inside of that state you set that action and you play
and you tick the player. So now you could see it would randomly play any animation from there.
And what I can do is I can force him to keep playing and the player will basically keep
playing. So now the timeline doesn't represent anything in my case, it's just runtime playing
animations. And then that's the character randomly picking an action every time it
finishes. Every time it reaches a state, it randomly picks an action. It will go not anywhere.
We did the same with the motion graph. We walked randomly the motion graph. It's exactly the same
concept here. Nothing really fancy is happening. So what we have is a motion graph that basically
It's a bunch of states, and in each of those states,
you could take a number of actions leading to the next state.
Now, what we want to do is to build a control policy that
will allow us to pick the best action to do,
depending on a certain target, a certain goal.
So if I want to have the character walking along
and being able to say, I want you to walk and go there.
Basically, that's the goal is to say,
I want him to walk and reach that point.
I will do the same stuff that they've done in this paper,
which says that they wanted to make the boxer, in this case,
walk along in the ring to reach the character
they had to box with.
So, what we will do is that
we will discretize the world around the character
and giving him a bunch of different targets
that are a bunch of goals you could reach.
So basically, we say there is a points,
20 centimeters in front of you,
find the best actions that will make sure
that we walk next to that point.
I will have another point that will be one meters away,
give me the best actions
that will actually make me reach that point
and so on and so on.
It's set up in a circle around the character that gives you a bunch of points that you
could start to find the best animations that will allow you to reach any of those points.
So at runtime, I will be able to say, I need you to go four decent minutes on your left
and then it will give me the best animation that allows me to do this kind of stuff.
To do this, basically what you do is that you create a reward function saying for every
of the possible actions I have, this is the one that gives me the best results compared
to the target you were asking me to do.
So what happened is that we have a reward function and that reward function is basically
depending on the states you are in
and the action you pick.
So for every states you are in
and for every action you can pick,
this is the score, this is the reward you will get.
And how they compute this one.
So basically what you have is the reward functions.
It depends on the states.
So the current state of the character.
It depends on the target state,
so which points am I trying to reach.
And then it depends on the action
that was taken by the avatar.
And what you try to do is you would basically take
the position of the character along the trajectory.
That's why I saved the trajectory
in local space to that action.
I will have the point along that trajectory
and the point from the target,
say the point 10 centimeters in front,
the one one meters in front and so on and so on.
And I compute the distance of those
and then put them through an exponential.
And then finally, I have the discount factor.
So it's a value that I will use to say
the longer the animation is,
the worst the reward gets.
So if you manage to reach the point in 10 frames,
it will be much better if you reach that target in 100 frames.
So because you get the exponential here,
it will go down fairly quickly,
depending on the length of the animations.
And then the reward will actually be the maximum value
you could find along that path.
I will say for that trajectory at some point,
it will be really close to my target.
So that will be the max t.
But again, it finds the best score
between long or short term and the closest positions.
So that will be the reward function that we'll be computing.
So what I would do is compute a bunch of stuff.
The first thing that I'm interested in
is knowing what is the maximum number of action
any states can take.
And actually I have one, at least one state
that has seven actions.
And the second one is the longest action I have
and the longest action is 23 frames.
So nearly one second of animations, the longest actions.
So as they have in the paper,
so they said I have a bunch of points around me.
So this is what I would do.
I will create the targets, positions.
So all the points around me,
So I'm starting from zero zeros,
and then I go in circle with different ranges,
and I get more points the further I am.
And so that gives me 64 different targets.
So 64 different goals I can reach.
And then I will compute the immediate reward.
So I will compute the reward
with the formula I had here.
So basically what you have,
you get the rewards for each state,
for each target, for all the maximum action count.
So all of my states have a different number of actions.
In this case, to make my life easier,
I just take the maximum.
So I create a big table,
even if most of those points will be minus one.
So a really bad reward,
basically because you're trying to take an action
that doesn't exist.
I get the minus one by default says that that would be the action you would never take.
And to win sometimes later, at the same time, I compute my next states. So what I do is that
I know the trajectory of each of my actions. So I know that if I was in the specific states
trying to reach a specific point and I played these specific actions, the next one anyway,
will always lead me to the same point and that will be that next state in the state space.
So what I've called a state space normally when you do reinforcement learning you get
a table of states and action and basically state count and target position count all becomes one
big state space. So if you check what I've done here is that I've computed everything using
the states and the targets separately and then the action. But then when I'm reaching here what I've
do is that I've reshaped the immediate reward and next states as being just a mix of all the
different states, states becoming in this case the character position and the target I was trying
to reach that becomes only one single state so that's why when I compute the next states I do
it this way so I get only one value the next state is one value is really one states right
so I have the immediate reward and the next states and so I can actually
load my gamepad. Okay. So I can use my pad now to control my character. And what I will do is I
will play the animation using that reward. So what happens is that if I don't have any action,
I check the states I'm in. And then from there, I compute the
I find the closest position, the closest target I can have. So
everything was computed in local space. So every time I'm in a state and I'm asking to reach a
certain point in world space, I need to convert that position relative to me
and then find the closest target I could get. So that's what I'm doing here. I convert the position
to be relative to me and then I take all the target positions and I try to find which one
I'm the closest one. So I take the distance and I find the minimum argument, the minimum argument
inside of that list that gives me the target state I'm trying to reach. And then I can just
pick the reward. So I go with my reward and I say I'm in this state with this target state,
I get a bunch of actions I can choose from, give me the one that gave me the best reward
and then that will be my action. And I get my selected positions and all that kind of stuff
just to let you see what I'm playing with. So what I have is this. I get a bunch of stuff on
the ground. So I get my ball, which is the target I'm trying to reach. All those little
transforms are all the different targets that are possible. And the big one is the one that
right now I'm trying to match because that's the closest one to the to the
sphere and so if I play my animation you could see what you have there and so
the the grid only moves every time there is a state and every time there is an
action that is taken so you could see it always tried to reach the closest one
and the the the black line is the trajectory projected on the ground that
represents the length of the action it takes and what it does. Now what you could see is that
with the immediate reward it kind of stay close to that red ball but really even if I move it
it tends to do whatever he wants. Every action it picked gives him the best solution to get
the closest to the target he wanted to be. But he might get stuck into a weird state instead of the
motion graph that means that even his best action would actually make him walk in the wrong
direction. So you could see that's what happened. He managed to get close. He reached a bunch of
states that had big locomotions. So he was able to walk but then he stuck on something that loops
and is not even able to come here. So right now my policy to only use the reward you get from
get me the best action is not really accurate, doesn't give me any good results.
And that's where we will start to talk about reinforcement learning itself. Now what you
want to realize is that the state and action we have now is actually what we call a mark
of decision process or MDP in short. And an MDP basically means that any action you can
take only depends on the state you are in. You don't care about the past and how you
reach that state, the only thing that matters is what is the goal you want to reach.
what are the actions that are available to you depending on the states you're in.
So it only looks forward. And so the Markov decision process basically has a state and has
a set of actions and you get the reward functions by taking one action depending on one state.
You get discount factor which basically says how important the future is
And then you get the transition functions that tell you, well, if I was in one state
and I took one action, what is the next state I'm in, basically.
And the goal of the MDP is to find a policy that basically maximizes the cumulative reward
along the future.
So the real function is this one.
You have your gamma again here that reduce.
at t0 means the first transition you take is the most important one and then every time you advance
one step further this one will decrease and you will have the reward for the next state that
picked the next action and then the reward for the next state that picked the next action and so
on and so on. And what we're trying to find is to maximize this sum of infinite possibilities
you'll have and find the best trajectory through all the states and actions you could take
that give you the maximum cumulative reward. That is impossible to compute because it's an
infinite sum, so we need to find a way to compute that kind of stuff and what we do usually is that
we use the value function. What is the value functions? It basically stores the best reward
you could have if you are in one state. So it gives you what you want to do. It basically tells you
the maximum score you could have to pick any of the actions you have because you are inside of one
state. So that's your immediate reward plus the discounting factor of the next state that already
knows what is the best action reward you can have. So it is an iterative process. Basically,
you have the immediate reward plus the future reward, but the future reward is actually computed
with the same value functions as the one that you have here at this point. And thanks to this
formulation, we have the Bellman update rules that basically says that you could just compute this
As long as your gamma is less than one, you could iteratively compute this stuff
and update the value every time you take one of the actions, you check the future,
you update your values to take another action, take the futures and so on.
And you can update your value functions and it will converge to a solution.
So it starts from picking randomly any state action pair,
compute the reward, estimate the value of the future reward,
and then update your value functions.
What I've done is that instead of have the value functions
that's only states and best actions,
what I would do is that I would have a value functions
that have the states and each of the action,
and I will compute all the actions separately.
It's just to make the code easier to read here.
So basically what you do is this,
you randomly pick any states, any action,
then you compute the length, you take the reward
and I've pre-computed the reward.
So at least I don't have to re-compute
that same reward as every time.
So I've pre-computed the reward, I get it.
I also pre-computed what was the next state.
So I already have the next state.
And I can find the maximum values.
So I will go from my value function that I'm computing,
get the next states, find what is the best value
I could ever dream of in that case,
and that's my next max.
And I can update my value function with a reward
plus the next max, plus the future reward discount.
And what they used as a discount was,
that's why yeah that's what that here so they've used the the gamma again and
it's multiplied directly by it's a power of the length of the animation again so
if your action is really long your future reward anyway is less
So instead of just taking the number of actions you took, it's actually the length of the animation itself that matters to reach.
Then you can see that I'm slowly converging because the amount of values I have in total in my value functions doesn't change,
even if I'm actually computing 30,000 different actions there spares, it did
converge and quite close to a conversion after 370 epochs, so I've
recomputed that value functions every time. And now that I have the value
function, well instead of picking the immediate reward as I was doing before, I
I can just use my value function
and then we could see if the future reward
makes the system a bit smarter
to go and pick the next animations.
So let's see.
Walking around, you could see that it goes back
to the blue sphere a bit faster
and if I give him a target now,
I would actually try to reach it a bit further
or at least null in straight line when I give him a target.
And I can start to annoy him a lot,
just changing direction all the time.
And as a reminder, if I go back to the immediate mode,
this is what happens, it tends to play
and live its own life, doesn't care about my targets.
And if I ask him to go back with the value functions,
here it is going back to the right direction.
And so we've trained our first animation controller,
basically it is now it has the value functions
that allow him to pick the next best action
using the future reward.
But something you might have noticed is that
in this case, I've actually been able to switch
from the immediate mode to the value functions.
And that's basically because when you train a policy
like this, the policy just tells you which action
you have to take depending on the states you're in.
And so you could use different sets of policies
depending on the stuff you want to do
inside of your, the same motion graph.
So you will have always the same states,
always the same actions.
The only thing you want to change
is how you pick the best action.
So something I don't really like in this case
is that is not really able to go on the target
and stays on the target.
What I want to do is to basically says
if you're close to the target,
you go in idle mode and you stop walking.
Unfortunately for me, I don't have in my motion graph
any idle animation,
because when we did the motion graph earlier,
it was to do locomotion.
So it basically works all the time.
But there is something at the end of my animation here
that basically says from frame 950 to frame 1200,
it would stay around this spot and just do small steps.
So what I would do is that instead of saying,
go in idle because I don't have any,
I would say, go play those frames of animation
when you're close to the target,
just stay close and play that.
So I could train another policy.
So what I would do is that instead of having my value
functions, the one that makes me walk,
I would do a second value function
that I would call value function static.
basically says, stay on the spot as best as you can.
And this one only depend on the states.
Now there is no target anymore.
It's really, it's just you are inside of an animation
and if I tell you to stop that the action
I wanted you to do, there is no targets anyway.
So my value functions is way smaller in this case.
It's only has state counts and max action count.
My reward itself is always zero, except if you were playing animations that started inside
of that range and ended inside of that range.
So really, I want you to play actions inside of the end of the range.
And that's it.
And then I propagate the same way I take the next states, find the next maximum score I
can have.
I have the same future reward discount,
depending on the length of the animations, all the same.
And then I can compute this reward.
And you can see that it convert really quickly
because basically everything is zero
and the end of the animation is one
and you just have to propagate those weights.
And now what I do is that I don't control
in which state I want to be manually.
The only thing that happens is that if I'm close to the goal,
If my position is close to the goal at just less than 50 centimeters,
I will start to use that policy that says stay next to it. And if I'm further away,
I use the walking policy to reach the goal. And so if I am here and I ask him to play,
this is what I would get. So the green one means stay in spot. And you can see it plays
basically that end of animations, it just stays and plays inside of those animations.
And the way the value function was computed, it even gives you best scores if it keeps
playing along in animations, because I would have a score of one for being inside an animation,
but I will get a big reward because the next one was also in the same range, and I will
get a big reward because the next one was also in the same range.
So it will tend to play forward.
You could see that even here,
that represent the frame I was playing,
that represent the transition is taking.
So you could see it keeps playing all the range
and then change every time to go back to the beginning.
So that's that loop to give him the best reward.
And if I move away, it will go
and it will start to walk into that direction.
And as long as if it gets close,
it goes back to the other one.
And I can come back here
And it will walk again, coming back to the targets
and stop to the targets.
So that's the advantage of having this kind of stuff.
You could change policies and depending on how you do,
see it walk too far, it gets closed again,
and so on and so on.
Because there is nothing that forces him to not drift
when he walks.
So it will actually, from time to time,
drift away from the target.
And that's it.
train two different policies on one motion graph and you could you could
think of any type of policies doing different stuff what they've done in the
paper that it was a boxing one so you have all the different points where you
can we can punch and you could of course ask him to punch a specific points and
it will move along punch it. Unfortunately, I didn't had enough punching animations inside of
my libraries. So I've stayed with the locomotion one. But there's a lot of stuff you could learn.
And starting from here, basically, what you will have is
two different directions that the paper will start to go. They will get the branch that will try to
to get a better motion graph with a lot more connections
inside of a motion graph,
because the more connections you have is the more states,
you have is the more is how quickly you could react
because it's all the time
you could actually take a decision.
You can only take decision at each action.
So you would try to have a higher number of connections
inside of your motion graph.
That's one of the direction.
Then you will get the other direction
we say, what we want to do is to find another type of structures that allow us to have more
and more actions, having actions smaller and smaller and smaller. And so you get the, you
could take decisions more often. And so the maximum range you could have is at some point
you will have that every frame would be a state and an action and you will be able to
take an action at every frame so that will be for in a few paper and basically what will happen
when you really have all this you will start to reach what the motion matching is which was
the next step says the first step was to say I remove the motion graph and I have value functions
that use reinforcement learning on. And then the motion matching would basically say,
well, I will remove the reinforcement learning, but I will still have basically a value functions.
We'll just see that it's not learned through the same process. It's extracted from the animations,
but the concepts are the same. So that's why I love to go through those steps
before reaching the motion matching. I hope you liked it and see you in our next paper about
animations and reinforcement learning that will be slightly different.